<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Detestable designs of France expos'd, or, The true sentiments of the Spanish Netherlanders representing the injustice of the King of France by his declaration of war against His Catholick Majesty, and the justice of the counter-declaration of the Marquess of Gastannaga his Governour General of the Low-Countries.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35796</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1212</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5366</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12795645</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12795645</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93977</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A35796)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93977)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 378:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Detestable designs of France expos'd, or, The true sentiments of the Spanish Netherlanders representing the injustice of the King of France by his declaration of war against His Catholick Majesty, and the justice of the counter-declaration of the Marquess of Gastannaga his Governour General of the Low-Countries.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>30, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Clavel ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisements: p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Louis --  XIV, --  King of France, 1638-1715.</term>
               <term>Charles --  II, --  King of Spain, 1661-1700.</term>
               <term>Gastañaga, Francisco Antonio de Agurto, --  marqués de, ca. 1641-1702.</term>
               <term>France --  Foreign relations --  1643-1715.</term>
               <term>France --  History --  Louis XIV, 1643-1715.</term>
               <term>Europe --  Politics and government --  1648-1715.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93977:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93977:1"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Deteſtable Deſigns of</hi> FRANCE EXPOS'D.</p>
            <p>Or, the True SENTIMENTS OF THE <hi>Spaniſh Netherlanders:</hi> The Injuſtice of the King of <hi>FRANCE</hi> BY HIS DECLARATION Of War againſt His Catholick MAJESTY, And the Juſtice of the COUNTER-DECLARATION of the Marqueſs of <hi>Gaſtannaga</hi> his Governour Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral of the <hi>Low-Countries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Clavel</hi> at the <hi>Peacock</hi> at the Weſt end of St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1689.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:93977:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:93977:2"/>
            <head>THE TRUE SENTIMENTS OF THE <hi>SPANISH NETHERLANDERS,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>FRANCE</hi> ſets her ſelf againſt all the World; and therefore it is but juſt that all the World ſhould declare againſt Her. She it is that makes the firſt Onſet, and we can do no leſs than defend our ſelves. Since the <hi>Germans</hi> in a little Treatiſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titled the <hi>French Herald,</hi> have ſo ſucceſsfully refell'd the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations of War made by he moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> King againſt the Emperour and the Pope, the <hi>Flemings</hi> are no leſs oblig'd to their Sovereign, and the <hi>Marqueſs of Gaſtannaga</hi> their Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. Nor are they in a worſe condition powerfully to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute all the weak and pitiful Arguments, with which the moſt Chriſtian King endeavour'd to ſupport his Pretenſions. After he had declar'd War againſt the Emperour, and at the ſame time againſt the Empire (for he ſeeks the utter extirpation of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi>) he has alſo declar'd War againſt the Catholick King by an Act of the fifteenth of this preſent year 1689. and at the ſame inſtant, has exercis'd all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Hoſtility upon his Dominions, as well in <hi>Flanders</hi> and the <hi>Low-Countreys,</hi> as in <hi>Catalonia.</hi> 'Tis very true, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he fell to work, there was no Stone which the Court of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:93977:3"/>
               <hi>France</hi> left unturn'd to corrupt the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Council, on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to draw them from their own Intereſts, and divide them from the Emperour. For She well knows that while the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> continues firmly united in the two Branches of <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> ſhe need not be afraid of any other Power: and therefore it is, that ſhe has attempted to divide them. So that after ſhe had declar'd War againſt <hi>Spain</hi> by the Exerciſe of moſt diſmal Hoſtilities, ſhe has labour'd to the utmoſt of her Power, to prevent the King of <hi>Spain</hi> from ſending ſuccour to his own Bloud and his own Family. This is abſolutely to tie one Arm to hinder the relief of the other which they are maiming at the ſame time. But be ſure that after <hi>Spain</hi> has ſat quietly to ſee the Empire devour'd, <hi>France</hi> them will turn her Arms upon him and perfect his deſtruction. 'Tis true, that <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. finding himſelf burthen'd with King <hi>James</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> who has thrown himſelf into his Arms, and drawn upon him a terrible War through the Union of the Forces of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> would fain lull <hi>Spain</hi> aſleep, and cajole the Emperor with vain hopes of peace, and by motives of Religion. His Miniſters have ſpared no Flatteries at the Court of <hi>Spain.</hi> He has offer'd the King of <hi>Spain</hi> to make him Arbitrator and Mediator of the Peace between him and the Empire. He has caus'd his Miniſters to lay before the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> that it is the Intereſt of the Catholick Religion before all things, to ſee the King of <hi>England</hi> re-eſtabliſh'd in his Dominions, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that it would be a work of infinite Charity. That the differences between the Emperour and him might be eaſily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termin'd by way of Negotiation, upon which Heaven would never fail to ſhed down a Bleſſing, ſo ſoon as their Intereſts were link'd together, by ſo pious a work, as would be that of reſtoring a Catholick King, diſpoſſeſs'd for the ſake of his Religion. The Miniſters of <hi>France</hi> at the coſt of <hi>Spain</hi> made uſe of all their Engins which were employ'd in <hi>Germany</hi> to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unite the Princes of the Empire. They laid before them, <q>That it was a real War for the ſake of Religion; That there was
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:93977:3"/>a League between the <hi>Lutheran</hi> Princes of <hi>Germany,</hi> the <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers</hi> and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> revolted from their lawful Sovereign, and that they menac'd no leſs the ruin of all the Catholick States, than of the Catholick Religion it ſelf.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And beſides all this, they made uſe of all thoſe perſons who had the neareſt Acceſs to his Catholick Majeſty, to inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate into him the great Advantages that would accrew to Both, if he and the Emperour ſhould join their Forces to thoſe of <hi>France</hi> againſt the Common Enemy. They farther whiſper'd him in the Ear, <q>That the <hi>Hollanders</hi> were not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd in their Inclinations by the Treaties of the Truce and Peace that had been brought to paſs ſince their Rebellion: That after all, they were but Rebellious Subjects, and that it always became him to make it his buſineſs to reduce them under their former Yoke: that their Maſter offer'd his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty the Aſſiſtance of his Forces to tame and bring them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſubjection and their old Obedience. That <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Holland</hi> made a Union formidable to all ſuch Princes who had any Territories bordering upon the Sea: That the King of <hi>Spain</hi> had great reaſon to fear the loſs of the <hi>Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands:</hi> That the <hi>Engliſh</hi> who had been in poſſeſſion of <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> not long ſince, would not be wanting to make themſelves Maſters of <hi>Newport</hi> and <hi>Oſtend,</hi> which when it ſhould come to paſs, they ſhould ſoon be Lords of <hi>Bruſſels</hi> and <hi>Antwerp:</hi> that there would be no ſecurity for <hi>Spain</hi> it ſelf. That her Coaſts lay naked and open as well upon the Ocean as the <hi>Mediter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranean</hi> Sea, and that ſhe would be always expos'd to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſions of the fierce and haughty <hi>Engliſh;</hi> and the Attempts of <hi>Holland</hi> always covetous, and ſeeking after nothing but Gain: That the two faithleſs Nations being Miſtreſſes of the Sea, would make an Eternal ſeparation between the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions of the King of <hi>Spain</hi> in the new diſcover'd VVorld, and thoſe which he has in <hi>Europe:</hi> That his Gallions would import no more Bullion into his Territories, but be ſnap'd by the way to gratifie the Luxury of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> who never
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:93977:4"/>think they have enough to ſupply their Debaucheries and Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feminacy: or elſe to aſſwage the Avarice of the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> who never believe they have Gold and Silver ſufficient in their Coffers: That they would never content themſelves with putting a ſtop to the flowing Rivolets, but would ſuddenly go to the Fountain it ſelf, and that the two Inſatiable and faithleſs Nations would wreſt even <hi>Peru</hi> it ſelf from the King of <hi>Spain.</hi>
               </q> But luckily for us, all theſe great Engins were broken to pieces by the conſtancy of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Council. Thereupon the Court of <hi>France</hi> being incenſed by the ill ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of their Intrigues, has declar'd War againſt the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and grounded their Declaration upon ridiculous Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, not much more ſolid than thoſe contain'd in their <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſto</hi> againſt the Emperour, to juſtifie their taking Arms a ſecond time.</p>
            <p>Let us a little examin this Declaration, and the better to diſcover the vanity of it, let us compare it with the Counter-Declaration of Monſieur the <hi>Marqueſs</hi> of <hi>Gaſtannaga</hi> our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſincere deſire,</hi> ſays the Declaration, <hi>which the King has had to obſerve the Truce concluded in the year</hi> 1684. <hi>has in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd his Majeſty to take no notice of the behaviour of the</hi> Spaniſh <hi>Miniſters in all the Courts of the Princes of</hi> Europe. It is apparent, that when a Man renounces all other Vertues, he abjures alſo all Shame and Modeſty. Of which if <hi>France</hi> had preſerv'd but the leaſt part in the World, ſhe would never have had the Confidence to ſay, <hi>That the King had a ſincere deſire to obſerve the Truce concluded in the Year</hi> 1684. Who is it then that has broken this Truce for which <hi>France</hi> had ſuch a profound Regard? VVas it the Emperour, who had nothing elſe in his thoughts, but onely vigorouſly to carry on his Affairs and Advantages a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the common Enemy of Chriſtendom? VVas it the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> who never ſtirred ſince, nor committed the leaſt Act of Hoſtility againſt <hi>France?</hi> And now at this
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:93977:4"/>preſent Juncture, who is it that declares the War, is it <hi>France</hi> or <hi>Spain?</hi> Is it not ſhe that declares the War who alſo brake the Truce? There needs no more but to call to mind what was ſaid in the <hi>Fecialis Gallus;</hi> and we ſhall eaſily find with what ſincerity the Court of <hi>France</hi> could affirm, <hi>That the King had a ſincere deſire to preſerve the Truce of</hi> 1684. There we ſhall obſerve, after the Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Truce, a continued train of offer'd Violences, which were all of them ſo many Breaches. There are no manner of wranglings, Menaces, or Intrigues which the Court of <hi>France</hi> has not made uſe of, to force the <hi>States</hi> of the Empire to conſent to this Truce; that is to ſay, to oblige them to renounce the Provinces of the Empire which the Violences and Invaſions of <hi>France</hi> had raviſh'd from them, on purpoſe to annex them to that Crown. It is the Marqueſs of <hi>Gaſtannaga</hi> who has moſt right to boaſt of the Fidelity of his King, and to ſay as he does, <q>That all the Treaties of Peace and Truce have been religiouſly obſerv'd, on the King our Maſter's part, and broken upon ſlight oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, and raſhly violated by <hi>France.</hi>
               </q> If it were lawful at any time to violate Treaties of Peace, it would be when the Peace was unjuſt, when they were made by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint of Force and Violence, or that they had been ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd by fraud and circumvention. Private Perſons have a right to ſeek redreſs of the bad Contracts they have made, when they have been loſers very never the full moiety. In truth, if <hi>Spain</hi> had not been ſincere; if ſhe had not had more reſpect to the Faith of Treaties than <hi>France,</hi> ſhe would have had juſt reaſon to ſeek her own relief, conſidering the enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous loſſes which ſhe had ſuſtain'd. Being abandon'd by her Allies, ſhe was conſtrain'd to loſe and let go three large Provinces, <hi>Franche Conte, Luxemburg,</hi> and almoſt all <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</hi> What Claim could <hi>France</hi> lay to thoſe ſpacious Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys? She had won them by Conqueſt. But can right of Conqueſt take place in an unjuſt VVar? He has then no
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:93977:5"/>more to do but to quarrel with his Neighbours, and to ſeize upon all their Eſtates for his own uſe by right of Conqueſt; and after all to reſtore them a ſmall portion, and detain the greateſt part to himſelf, and then to ſay, That he has a juſt Title to what he poſſeſſes, becauſe he has won it by the Sword, and that he was very kind in reſtoring a part of what he had Conquer'd. Between private Perſons ſuch ſort of dealings would be look'd upon as perfect Robbery: and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed between Kingdom and Kingdom it is no leſs than ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Highway-Felony, and meer Uſurpation: and <hi>Spain</hi> being conſtrain'd by force to ſubmit to Treaties ſo unjuſt, might have had grounds ſufficient to look upon them as null and void.</p>
            <p>The moſt Chriſtian King ſays, <hi>That the Miniſters of</hi> Spain <hi>in the Courts of</hi> Europe, <hi>made it their ſole buſineſs to excite them, to take up Arms againſt</hi> France, <hi>and that his Majeſty was not ignorant of the part which they had in the Negotiation of the League of</hi> Auſpur4gh. Once more, ſuppoſing this to be true, it was impoſſible to attribute this to <hi>Spain</hi> for a Crime: She did not concede that large and conſiderable Part of her Territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries to <hi>France</hi> till conſtrain'd by Force: Now Force has no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to do with Right. She had not parted with thoſe ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Provinces, but onely becauſe the Princes of <hi>Europe,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſwayed by various Motives, and carried away by other Intereſts and Affairs, abandon'd her Party. Was it a Crime in <hi>Spain</hi> to labour the reknitting of an Aſſociation together, which ought never to have been broken, till they had reduc'd <hi>France</hi> to Reaſon, and brought down her Pride?</p>
            <p>But beſides this, all that <hi>France</hi> ſpeaks to this purpoſe is meer ſuppoſition. Monſieur our Governour has much more reaſon to underſtand the conduct of <hi>Spain</hi> in forein Courts, than the Miniſters of <hi>France.</hi> He averrs and is ready to prove that the Catholick King has religiouſly obſerv'd the Treaties. The Miniſters of <hi>Spain</hi> have maintain'd in the Courts of <hi>Europe,</hi> that it behoves them to be jealous of the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:93977:5"/>Grandeur of <hi>France.</hi> This they could not do, without having a deſign to break the Truce, but 'twas onely upon the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of preſerving the Peace. This was that which was aim'd at by the League of <hi>Auſpurgh:</hi> By this League they intended to bridle <hi>France,</hi> oblige her to live in peace; and to preſerve a Right in the Empire of re-demanding what had been diſmember'd from it; when the Truce for twenty years ſhould come to be expir'd. Now in the language of the Court of <hi>France</hi> this is ſaid to be a Violation of the Peace and Truce: for whatever ſets bounds and limits to her unruly Ambition violates all Divine and humane Laws. Laſtly, in a word, that we may underſtand who ſpeaks moſt Truth, whether the moſt Chriſtian King, in ſaying, <hi>That he had a ſincere Intention to preſerve the Truce,</hi> or the Marqueſs of <hi>Gaſtannaga,</hi> who aſterts hove us to conſider who it was, that after the Peace of <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meghen</hi> firſt began to wrangle with his Neighbours, who iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu'd forth his Proceſſes concerning the Limits; who demanded Compenſations for the Territories included with in the <hi>Spaniſh Flanders;</hi> who ſet up his Gallowſes at the Gates of <hi>Namur;</hi> who aſſerted his Right, by the burning and ſacking of all the Country: who threw in his Bombs into <hi>Oudenard,</hi> in a time of ſetled Peace; who it was that caus'd the Chamber of <hi>Metz</hi> to adjudg him the two Thirds or three Fourths of the Dependences of <hi>Luxenburgh.</hi> If the King of <hi>Spain</hi> had acted any ſuch thing, they had done him wrong, who ſaid, <hi>That he had religiouſly obſerv'd the Treaties.</hi> But if it were the King of <hi>France</hi> who was the Author of all thoſe Violences, it is a moſt unjuſt thing in him to Aſſert in the face of the World, <hi>That he has always had a ſincere deſire to obſerve the Treaties.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it is not enough for the Court of <hi>France</hi> to have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus'd in general all the Miniſters and Governours of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick King of having violated the Treaty, unleſs our Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour Monſieur the Marqueſs of <hi>Gaſtannaga</hi> be charg'd in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular. His Majeſty ſays, the Declaration <hi>has been</hi> alſo inform'd
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:93977:6"/>of the part which the Governour of the <hi>Low-Countries</hi> had in the Enterprize which the Prince of <hi>Orange undertook againſt</hi> England.</p>
            <p>By this it appears, that his moſt Chriſtian Majeſty had very good Eyes to ſee what no body elſe but himſelf could diſcover. But I would fain underſtand what part the Marqueſs of <hi>Gaſtannaga</hi> had in the Enterprize of the Prince of <hi>Orange;</hi> Did he righ out any of his Maſters Ships to join the <hi>Holland</hi> Fleet? Did he levy any Soldiers in the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> or ſend any Forces aboard to land in <hi>England?</hi> Did he lend any Money to the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> or the <hi>Hollanders</hi> toward their getting ready their Fleet? Did he ſollicit the <hi>Engliſh</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volt and favour that pretended Invaſion? In my opinion theſe are the only Acts, by which it may be preſum'd that he had any part in the Enterprize. Now it is as clear as Daylight, and notorious to all <hi>Europe,</hi> that the Governour of the <hi>Netherlands</hi> was never guilty of any of theſe Charges, and that he cannot be upbraided with any falſe ſtep that ever he made either directly or indirectly to the ruine of King <hi>James:</hi> but I will tell ye the truth how it was.</p>
            <p>Some years ſince there was a <hi>Tribunal</hi> erected at <hi>Verſailles</hi> altogether reſembling the Judgment-Seat of God; where men were to anſwer for their Thoughts as well as their Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. In this <hi>Tribunal,</hi> which underſtood the hearts of Men, it was, that they found that the Marqueſs of <hi>Gaſtannaga,</hi> was at the bottom of his heart very glad, that the King of <hi>England</hi> had work enough to do at home, ſince he minded ſo little thoſe Affairs abroad that moſt concern'd him. For King <hi>James</hi> was <hi>Garrantee</hi> for the Peace of <hi>Nimeghen,</hi> for the obtaining of which his Brother had been the Mediatour. It behov'd him alſo to be <hi>Garantee</hi> for the Truce that follow'd: and yet he ſat ſtill without ever concerning himſelf, while the King of <hi>France</hi> both openly broke the Truce and invaded the Empire. It is natural not to cloſe too far with the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts of thoſe, who do not cloſe with ours; eſpecially when
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:93977:6"/>they are obliged thereto. It may be that the Marque4ſs of <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtannaga,</hi> who is deeply engaged in the Intereſts of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, not a little perplex'd that the King of <hi>England</hi> ſo ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neglected the peace of <hi>Europe,</hi> was nothing at all troubl'd to ſee him depriv'd of that Peace himſelf, which he would not preſerve to others. This was a Thing divin'd in <hi>France,</hi> as it was divin'd that the Emperour would make a Peace with the <hi>Turk,</hi> to make War upon the <hi>Rhine.</hi> And this was the great Crime of the Governour of the <hi>Low-Countreys.</hi> He was a Friend to the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> before the enterprize of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> nor has he yet abandon'd his Friendſhip, but has al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways preſerv'd the good Correſpondence which was between the Prince and Him. This was another of his Crimes. For from this time forward the World is to be inform'd, that <hi>France</hi> is not onely the Arbitratour and judg of the general concluſions of Peace, but ſhe is alſo the Miſtreſs of private and particular tyes and Obligations of Friendſhip: People of honeſty and Integrity are no longer to have any other Friends but thoſe whom ſhe will allow them. Otherwiſe he muſt be a Criminal, a Violator of Treaties, and an Infringer of Alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances. It may be that the Marqueſs of <hi>Gaſtannaga,</hi> at what time there was no news in <hi>Holland</hi> of what paſs'd in <hi>England,</hi> gave advice to the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Miniſter reſiding at the <hi>Hague</hi> of what Intelligence he had by the way of <hi>Newport,</hi> and that the News was carry'd to the Princeſs of <hi>Orange</hi> and the <hi>States.</hi> And this was having a part in the Enterprize of the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> according to the Interpretation of <hi>France:</hi> for that without this Intelligence the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s Enterprize could never have ſucceeded: this was that which terrify'd King <hi>James:</hi> this was that which caus'd him to abdicate his Kingdom: this was that which had ſuch an influence upon his Army that they refus'd to fight; in a word, this was that which did the work.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:93977:7"/>
            <p> Thus it is, that <hi>France</hi> derides and laughs at all the World, and takes us all for a company of Beaſts: Nevertheleſs theſe ſpecious Pretences are the Ingredients of a Delcaration of War, and make up the principal Grounds and foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of it.</p>
            <p>Now let us liſten to the following part of the Declaration: <q>His Majeſty not being able to believe that the conduct of the Governour of the <hi>Low-Countries</hi> in this particular Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair, was every by the Directions of Order of the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> who by ſo many ties of Religion, Bloud, and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of all Kings one toward another, was oblig'd to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a Uſurpation of that nature; His Majeſty was in hopes that he might have been able to perſuade his moſt Chriſtian Majeſty to a Union for the Re-eſtabliſhment of the lawful King in <hi>England</hi> and the preſervation of the Catholick Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion againſt the Proteſtant League, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> His Majeſty was inform'd at the ſame time, that the Spaniſh Ambaſſadour in <hi>England,</hi> was every day with the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> &amp;c. And bad Counſels prevailing, his Majeſty had intelligence that a reſolution was taken to favour the Uſurper of <hi>England,</hi> and to join with the Proteſtant Prince.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Behold another moſt pious and moſt Catholick Article of the Declaration: and now after this who can ever accuſe the King of <hi>France</hi> of not behaving himſelf anſwerable to his Title of <hi>Moſt Chriſtian?</hi> It is clear from hence that the King of <hi>Spain</hi> is no longer to be accounted Catholick, ſince he is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Friend and favourer of the Proteſtants. He refuſes to ſuccour a Catholick Prince diſpoſſeſs'd by an Uſurper: he joins his Forces with thoſe of the Enemies of the Church. Nevertheleſs, the Marqueſs of <hi>Gaſtannaga</hi> does not reliſh this ſpecious Article. And therefore he finds himſelf oblig'd to tell the VVorld in his Counter Declaration, <q>That that ſame piece of the moſt Chriſtian King is injurious to the Devotion and Piety of his Maſter, as being labour'd with all the Art imaginable to render his Alliances wih the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:93977:7"/>Princes and States his Neighbours, ſcandalous to the World.</q>
            </p>
            <p>In the Declaration of the moſt Chriſtian King, of which we have already repeated the words, it appears that his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty ſeems to have a peculiar abhorrence of Uſurpers, and would by no means be thought a friend to Uſurpations, but altogether a Zealot for the Rights and Priviledges of lawful Sovereigns. For he calls the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> a <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper,</hi> and would have all the World to be his Enemy. King <hi>James</hi> he calls the Lawful King of <hi>England,</hi> and would have all the World to ſuccour him. But it is an eaſie thing to look through all theſe feigned ſhews of his good Nature; for if they be real, 'tis to be hop'd that the conſideration of theſe things will bring him to look homeward, conſult his own Actions, and that then he will ſuddenly make ſatisfaction to the Princes his Neighbours, for ſo many Provinces of theirs which he himſelf has uſurp'd: He will reſtore <hi>Franche Conté,</hi> the Dutchy of <hi>Luxenburgh,</hi> and all <hi>Flanders</hi> to the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick King. He will ſurrender <hi>Strasburgh, Friburgh,</hi> the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latinate,</hi> and all the <hi>Rhine</hi> to the <hi>Empire,</hi> and <hi>Lorain</hi> to it's own natural and lawful Prince and Duke. For how is it poſſible that the declared Enemy of Uſurpers and Uſurpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſhould himſelf continue to be the greateſt Uſurper of all? King <hi>James,</hi> he ſays, was lawful King of <hi>England;</hi> — it may be ſo — Neither do we concern our ſelves whether he were or no. — But was not the Catholick King as much the Lawful Sovereign of both the <hi>Burgundies?</hi> Is it becauſe that <hi>Flanders</hi> which was wreſted from him during the Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paignes of 1667. and the reſt that follow'd, was not his by all manner of Right and Title? Is it becauſe he was not the true and lawful Duke of <hi>Luxenburgh?</hi> which was came the Duke of <hi>Lorain</hi> to forfeit his Dutchy? What right had the <hi>French</hi> to raviſh <hi>Strasburgh</hi> for the <hi>Empire?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Who ſhall endure the</hi> Gracchi <hi>complaining of Sedition?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:93977:8"/>
            <p> In good truth it is a thing altogether inſupportable, that a prince uſurping with ſo much Violence and Injuſtice the Eſtates of all the World, ſhould complain ſo loudly of Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, and of our being ſo ſtrictly united with them. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> is a Prince of the Bloud of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> he marry'd the next Heireſs; and he was called in by the Nation in General. He was declared King by the Three Eſtates of the Kingdom. Now had the <hi>French</hi> King any Veil like this to cover his Uſurpation of ſeveral Provinces, which being join'd together, are as good as a Kingdom? Our Eyes are not yet ſufficiently open to ſee the difference between the King of <hi>France</hi> and a Uſurper. He wreſted thoſe Countries from <hi>Spain,</hi> from the <hi>Empire,</hi> from the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> in open War and by the dint of Sword? VVhat other way did <hi>Crowwel,</hi> the moſt Infamous of all Uſurpers, aſcend the Throne of <hi>England?</hi> Was it not by the force of open VVar, and with his Arms in his hand? By what means did the <hi>Turks</hi> uſurp the Eſtates of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Princes? Was it not by main force? Therefore they are no Uſupers. And Excellent Definition of an Uſurper. If fraud be requir'd to make a Uſurper, was there ever known a more wicked piece of Treachery than that by which he got <hi>Strasburgh,</hi> and all the re-united Countries? But ſome will ſay, the King of <hi>France</hi> is too Conſcientious; he would not have deſpoil'd a King, he would not have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thron'd the King of <hi>England.</hi> A moſt apparent piece of Truth! It was the niceneſs of his Conſcience, I warrant ye, that hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd hi from taking <hi>Bruſſels</hi> and <hi>Antwerp</hi> as he did <hi>Gaunt;</hi> or as if he would not have taken <hi>Madrid,</hi> if it had been in his power, as well as <hi>Meſſina.</hi> While we ſee him devour, we ſee that he is Inſatiable; let him but alone till his hunger is aſſwaged, and you ſhall ſee how far he will eat on. If <hi>Caſtile</hi> had call'd him, and made him King, he would have gone thither f poſſible he could, and would have conquer'd
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:93977:8"/>it was he conquer'd <hi>Sicily.</hi> After all this, you may, if you pleaſe, give ear to the moſt Chriſtian King, when he talks ſo like a Chriſtian againſt Uſurpers.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs, we ought not to refuſe him the Honour of being an Enemy to Proteſtant Uſurpers. For that is a double Crime in a Catholick King to favour a Uſurper and a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Uſurper: that's very bad indeed. Yet we ſee that the moſt Chriſtian King has chang'd his Principles, and that we need not to be afraid, for the future, of his doing what he has done formerly. We might very well ſet before his Eyes <hi>tekely,</hi> the Uſurper of <hi>Hungary,</hi> who obtain'd that Title to be given him by the <hi>Ottoman Port,</hi> and who has done his utmoſt endeavour to get poſſeſſion of it. That Uſurper is a <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> for he is a <hi>Lutheran.</hi> Nevertheleſs the moſt Chriſtian King muſt not diſown but that he has acknowledg'd him for one of his beſt Friends. Had <hi>France</hi> no other Veil to hide her Miſcarriages than a Cobweb, yet ſhe is ſo brazen-fat'd, that ſhe would deny what ſhe did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind that Curtain, with the ſame confidence as if ſhe had had a wall of a hundred foot thick to conceal her. And therefore it is that you will find her perhaps denying all her ſtrict ties of Friendſhip and Treaty with <hi>Tekely</hi> and the <hi>Turk.</hi> But what will ſhe ſay to her Union with <hi>Cromwel?</hi> Here is an Example that nearly concerns <hi>England,</hi> where now the Diſpute lies. <hi>Henry William</hi> of <hi>Naſſau,</hi> Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> Prince of the Bloud of <hi>England,</hi> marry'd to <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> Eldeſt Daughter of <hi>James,</hi> call'd in by the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> Crown'd King by the three Eſtates is a Uſurper. He is a Proteſtant; Let every Catholick be anathematiz'd that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heres to him.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Cromwel,</hi> a Perſon of mean Extraction, yet a Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant; but the Abomination of all of his own Religion, the Murtherer of his King, whoſe Head he had cut off upon a publick Scaffold; The Tyrant of <hi>England,</hi> and ſworn Enemy of all Catholicks, is no Uſurper. It is lawful for a moſt
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:93977:9"/>Chriſtian King to make a League Offenſive and Defenſive with him, to give him Entrance into <hi>Flanders,</hi> to invite him to invade the Countries of a Catholick Prince, to deliver <hi>Dunkirk</hi> into his Hands, and give it to that ſame <hi>Engliſh</hi> Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. At that time <hi>the Motives and Inducements of Religion, Bloud,</hi> and ſafety of all <hi>Sovereign Princes</hi> were but Chime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra's: never any ſuch tings really known in the World till the moſt Chriſtian King begins to be afraid of <hi>England</hi> under the Government of the Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi> 'Tis a Crime for a Catholick King to have any Alliance with ſuch a Perſon. In good truth, it is apparent that the moſt Chriſtian King derides Religion and Chriſtianity; and laughs at all <hi>Europe</hi> beſide.</p>
            <p>Let us ſuppoſe the Catholick King to be at a loſs: behold him between two Uſurpers; between the King of <hi>France;</hi> a Uſurper without the leaſt ſhadow of Pretence, of two Dutchies, two great Provinces, and ſeveral Cities and Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories, and between <hi>Henry William</hi> of <hi>Naſſau,</hi> Uſurper of <hi>England,</hi> as <hi>France</hi> pretends. The moſt Chriſtian King in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites him, <hi>by all the Motives of Religion, Bloud, and ſafety of Kings, to unite with him in a War againſt the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper of</hi> England: <hi>at leaſt if the Condition of his Affairs will not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit him to engage in ſuch a <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion, to obſerve and exact Neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trality.</hi> On the other ſide, King <hi>William</hi> of <hi>England</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes him great Advantages, if he will join with Him. What ſhall the Catholick King do? In my Opinion, between one Uſurper and t' other, his Intereſt requires him to declare for the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper,</hi> that never took any thing from him, againſt the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper</hi> that has wreſted from him by force ſo conſiderable a part of his Dominions. VVhat can <hi>France ſay to This?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to ſay no more of the pretended Uſurpation of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> who has told <hi>France</hi> that the Catholick King has join'd with a Uſurper? He has united with the Emperor his Kinſman and Ally; He has join'd with the Pope, the Head of the Church: Againſt whom? Againſt the common Enemy of the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:93977:9"/>Empire, againſt the general Enemy of <hi>Europe,</hi> againſt the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd Enemy of the Holy Empire. Where is the Scandal? The Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> lawful Elected, King of <hi>England</hi> by the Three Eſtates of the Kingdom, is upon his March the ſame way. What ſort of Morals has the Court of <hi>France</hi> found out to prove, that it is not lawful for the Catholick King to make an Alliance with him in defence of the Common Liberty of <hi>Europe?</hi> Is it for us to diſpute the Rights of the People and Kings of <hi>England?</hi> We ſhould take it very ill that the Engliſh ſhould intermeddle with the Government of <hi>Caſtile</hi> or <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragon.</hi> If there be any wrong done, 'tis done by all the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Now I cannot find that the whole Body of a Nation is anſwerable for its Conduct to any other than God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. If King <hi>James</hi> have any right on his ſide, we will not take it ill, that he defend his Title. But this is a Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel to be diſputed between the People and Him, wherein no body has to do to concern himſelf; much leſs the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick King, who never receiv'd any Kindneſs, but all the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage that might be from the late Kings of <hi>England,</hi> as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing always in League with <hi>France</hi> to the ruine of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria.</hi> This is the firſt time for theſe two hundred years paſt, that the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> has found <hi>England</hi> in a condition to be advantageous to their Intereſts: and <hi>France</hi> is mighty unwilling that they ſhould lay hold of the Lucky Conjuncture. 'Tis very unjuſt: and the Accuſation which the moſt Chriſtian King raiſes thereupon, is a Pretence with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ground.</p>
            <p>After all, what would be the benefit of that plauſible Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance into which his moſt Chriſtian Majeſty tells us, that <hi>he has labour'd ſo much to perſuade the Catholick King for the reſtoring King</hi> James? It would produce a bloudy War. <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> environ'd with the Sea, united to <hi>Holland,</hi> and in Alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with other Proteſtant Princes is able to maintain a War againſt all the other Princes of <hi>Europe.</hi> And in this War <hi>Spain</hi> would be a loſer, the Empire would get nothing, and <hi>France</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:93977:10"/>would win all. For when the Allies were weaken'd by extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagant Expences and a tedious War with <hi>England,</hi> then would <hi>France</hi> fall upon them and level all before him. This is a true Proſpect of the Deſigns of <hi>France,</hi> ſo Religious, ſo Catholick, ſo Zealous for the Rights of lawful Sovereigns.</p>
            <p>And now, has not the Marqueſs of <hi>Gaſtannaga</hi> juſt reaſon to publiſh, That the moſt Chriſtian King's Declaration <hi>is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious to his Catholick Majeſty, while it labours to render all his Alliances with the Princes and States his Neighbours ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous to all the World, whoſe glorious Aim is onely the repoſe of Chriſtendom, and the reciprocal Grandeur of each others Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi> The Scandal then being wip'd away, as it is clear there is none in this caſe, it is as apparent that his Catholick Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty cannot diſpence with his entring into an Alliance with all the Enemies of <hi>France,</hi> let them be of what Religion they will. For this Union tends to the glorious End, which is the ſafety and repoſe of <hi>Europe,</hi> of which the moſt Chriſtian King has been the Diſturber for ſeveral years. His Ambition is boundleſs, nor will it admit of any Limits: and therefore it is requiſite that Bounds ſhould be ſet him in ſpite of his teeth, <hi>it being neceſſary,</hi> as the Marqueſs of <hi>Gaſtannaga</hi> ſays, <hi>for the reciprocal Grandeur of each others Dominions.</hi> Not that the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour or the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> or their Allies have any deſign of Conqueſt upon thoſe Princes that acknowledge and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip Jeſus Chriſt. That Honour is left for the moſt Chriſtian King, to pillage and devour the Children of the Church. The Emperour is contented with conquering the Countries of the Chriſtians out of the hands of Infidels. And as for his Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Majeſty, all that he deſires, is but to regain what has been ſo unjuſtly raviſh'd from him. Nor does it appear that the Proteſtant States, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Hollanders</hi> either have or can have any proſpect of Conqueſt, nor any other Intereſt than that of the publick ſafety and the preſervation of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of <hi>Europe.</hi> But to be an Enemy of <hi>France,</hi> to go about to ſtop the Career of her Fury, is to declare War againſt Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:93977:10"/>if you will believe the Miniſters and Council of <hi>Verſailles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>His Majeſty was inform'd at the ſame time, that the</hi> Spaniſh <hi>Embaſſadonr in</hi> England <hi>was continually with the Prince of</hi> Orange. And thus for the future the Court of <hi>France</hi> it ſeems will take upon her to regulate the Viſits and motions of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Embaſſadours in Foreign Courts, ſo that they ſhall not dare to pay common Civilities without her permiſſion. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhould the Catholick King forbear holding that good Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence with the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> which he had always obſerv'd while he was at the <hi>Hague:</hi> Had the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> given the King any occaſion to order his Miniſters not to ſee him any more? 'Tis very true, the behaviour of the Prince was quite different toward Monſieur <hi>Barillon,</hi> the moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian King's Embaſſadour; for he ſent him away packing with ignominy: and he had good reaſon ſo to do. For that Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour was ſent into <hi>England</hi> for nothing elſe but to engage King <hi>James</hi> in a Conduct entirely oppoſite to the Intereſts of <hi>Europe</hi> and the publick peace. 'Twas his buſineſs to cheat <hi>England,</hi> and to tie he Hands that ſhe might not oppoſe the Ambitious deſigns of the moſt Chriſtian King: and aſter the flight of King <hi>James,</hi> he ſtaid behind for nothing elſe but to be a Spy and a Firebrand of Sedition. But the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour was there to engage <hi>England</hi> to do her duty, by ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Attempts of <hi>France.</hi> The Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> comes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>England,</hi> and by the flight of King <hi>James</hi> becomes Maſter of Affairs, and turns the Tide, ſo that the Revolution proves altogether favourable to the Intereſts of his Catholick Majeſty and of all <hi>Europe.</hi> What reaſon has the moſt Chriſtian King to take it ill that we ſhould lay hold of ſuch a lucky Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, for the reſtoring Chriſtendom to peace, and that flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing Condition which it formerly enjoy'd?</p>
            <p>One of the King of <hi>France</hi>'s Reaſons for declaring War againſt the Catholick King is, <hi>That the Governour of the</hi> Spaniſh Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands <hi>we very buſie in raiſing new Forces.</hi> Is not this very fine, that the King of <hi>France</hi> ſhall cover Land and Sea with
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:93977:11"/>Armies and Fleets, ſhall declare War againſt the Pope and the Emperor, threaten the Univerſe, make preparations as if he were to conquer all the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> and that he Princes of Chriſtendom and their Governours muſt not dare to make moderate Levies for their own ſecurity, but that the King of <hi>France</hi> muſt take from thence and occaſion to declare War againſt them? The Method of this Ambitious Prince is to ſtrike without giving notice, and to take, and burn Cities and Towns without any Declaration, as was apparent by the burning of <hi>Genoa,</hi> and the ſeizing of <hi>Strasburgh</hi> and <hi>Philipsburgh</hi> which he has wreſted from the Empire. However it behoves us to truſt to his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty, we muſt neither ſtir, nor make any Levies in the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands,</hi> becauſe that at the Court of <hi>Madrid</hi> he is endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to lull the People aſleep with Propoſals of Peace and Neutrality. It was alſo a very great Crime in the Governour of the <hi>Low-Countries</hi> to let in the <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>Brandenburgh</hi> Forces into the principal <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Cities of <hi>Flanders.</hi> Is it not a wonderful thing that we ſhould be ſo Cautious againſt a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Enemy? 'Tis true, that ſince there was no War declar'd between <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> it behov'd our Governour to live and ſleep at his eaſe, upon the Faith and ſecurity of the Treaties, ſince there was no neceſſity for him, to put Forein Forces in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his fortify'd Cities. But who is there that does not know that there is no Faith or Truſt in <hi>France;</hi> That Treaties of Truce and Peace, Capitulations and Promiſes are but Ropes of Chaff, which ſhe breaks in the firſt fits of her Fury and Ambition, without giving warning to any body.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>France</hi> alſo has found out another great Motive to declare War againſt <hi>Spain,</hi> for that ſhe has diſcover'd, <hi>That the Agent of the Prince of</hi> Orange <hi>have receiv'd conſiderable ſums at Cas</hi> diz <hi>and</hi> Madrid. In good truth we are become very happy-and now the Credit of the Crown of <hi>Spain</hi> is again reſtor'd. The pretended weakneſs of the Catholick King, <hi>the Poverty of is exhauſted Treaſuries, and the ſlowneſs of his Returns for the</hi> Low-Countries were the ſubjects of the Scoffs and Raillery
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:93977:11"/>of <hi>France.</hi> Now, thanks be to Heaven, <hi>Spain</hi> is in a condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to furniſh Foreiners with conſiderable Sums. And what is this to the King of <hi>France?</hi> Who ever heard it ſaid, that when Men pay their Debts, or borrow money of their Friends, that they incur the Crime of Infidelity toward thoſe with whom they are otherwiſe at Peace. This very Act of <hi>Spain</hi> in pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing money to the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> is a ſufficient proof that ſhe never intended to break the Truce firſt. For upon Emer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent occaſions every body has need of his own.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, <hi>France</hi> has found out that the Catholick King de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd the utmoſt of her Indignation, and that he ſhould be proceeded againſt with Fire and Sword, becauſe at leaſt, <hi>He would not oblige himſelf to obſerve and exact Neutrality, and not promiſe to ſuccour-her Enemies either directly or indirectly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis a very ſtrange thing that <hi>France</hi> will take upon her to bind up other States by Treaties upon Treaties, and obſerve none her ſelf. What need was there of a Treaty of Neutra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, ſince the Truce of 1684. was ſtill in force in reſpect of the Catholick King? And if <hi>France</hi> intended to make any ſatisfaction to the Empire for the diſmal Invaſion of <hi>Germany,</hi> would not things be in their former condition without any need of a Neutrality? But <hi>France</hi> refuſing to give the Emperour and the Pope ſatisfaction; was not this an uncivil, diſhoneſt and ridiculous Demand, that the King of <hi>Spain</hi> ſhould look on quietly and without ſtirring while <hi>France</hi> puſh'd forward her furious Attempts againſt the Emperour and the Pope, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt whom the moſt Chriſtian King had declar'd War? Can this be any occaſion to break a Treaty of Peace, becauſe <hi>France</hi> would not ſtay to ſee which way the Catholick King intended? For ſeeing <hi>France</hi> had Enemies enough to deal with, tho the Catholick King had forborn to meddle in the Affair, and that he had waited to ſee the end of the Quarrel and the ſucceſs of the War without having any hand in it, the moſt Chriſtian. King had what he could deſire. The Truce had been in force, and the Neutrality by conſequence. If his Catholic Majeſty
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:93977:12"/>had at length declar'd War againſt <hi>France,</hi> he had had time e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough then to think of defending him himſelf. So that this Declaration of VVar againſt <hi>Spain</hi> had not engag'd the moſt Chriſtian King in new Expences: ſeeing that having a War with <hi>Holland</hi> he was oblig'd to have an Army in the <hi>Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands.</hi> But the King of <hi>France</hi> thought to perform an Act of great courage and boldneſs, by being beforehand with the Male contents, and foremoſt in declaring a War againſt all the States which he foreſaw could give him any trouble, as in the gaiety of his Heart, he declar'd War at one time both againſt the Pope and the Emperour, fearing they would make a Peace with the <hi>Turk</hi> to fall upon him. Preſently after he declar'd War againſt the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> who were buſie about their own affairs, becauſe he foreſaw, that in the concluſion, it would not a little perplex him, ſhould they engage in the Intereſts of the Empire. And at length he declar'd War againſt his Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Majeſty at a time when he obſerv'd the Truce, becauſe he thought he could not prevent his aſſiſting the Emperour, his Kinſman and Ally. 'Tis a wonder that this Magnificent Braggard ſuffer'd <hi>England</hi> to get the ſtart of him. and that he let King <hi>William</hi> be the firſt that declar'd the War. We ſhall ſee how this <hi>Hectoring</hi> and Bouncing will thrive with the moſt Chriſtian King. He has had the pleaſure of declaring VVar a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all <hi>Europe,</hi> and to give the firſt Blows; we ſhall know ſhortly who will ſtrike hardeſt and continue longeſt in breath. And thus much for the reaſons upon which the King of <hi>France</hi> grounds his Declaration of VVar. There are others but I omit them, becauſe they are ſo very weak, that they are not worth repeating.</p>
            <p>Our Governour in his <hi>Counter-Declaration</hi> does not bring ſo many; but they are much better and more ſatisfactory. He grounds his <hi>Counter-Declaration</hi> only upon two Arguments: </p>
            <p>The firſt, <hi>That the Arms of</hi> France <hi>inhumanly and with all manner of cruelties and unheard of Barbariſms lay deſolate all the States of the Empire, without any regard to the Laws of Religion or War, or the ſacred Right of Capitulations.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:93977:12"/>
            <p> The Second, <hi>That the Miniſters of</hi> France <hi>make uſe of all the tricks and ſlights of Negotiation, and of all other means to diſturb the Harmony of Chriſtendom, and to bring in the whole</hi> Ottoman <hi>Power to the Deſtruction of</hi> Hungary, <hi>and at the ſame time to ranverſe the Peace concluded between his Imperial Majeſty, his Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious Allies and the</hi> Ottoman <hi>Port.</hi> Upon this ſecond Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon we could enlarge very much, if all had not been ſaid alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy that is to be ſpoken; that is to ſay, how juſtly and how truly we have Reaſon to complain of the Infamous Alliances between the Court of <hi>France</hi> and the <hi>Turk,</hi> to the Ruin of Chriſtendom. We are convinc'd of it by Letters intercepted, and undeniable proofs of the private Correſpondence, which they have always held with the Rebels of <hi>Hungary;</hi> and their furniſhing them with the Aſſiſtance both of Men and Money, and all this, ſince the General Peace of <hi>Nimeghen.</hi> We know that it was <hi>France</hi> that ſollicited the <hi>Port</hi> to invade the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror's Dominions, and to undertake the Siege of <hi>Vienna.</hi> We know that it was <hi>France</hi> that practiſed whatever could be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis'd to break the Peace between the Emperor and the Turk. All this is ſo notorious, that there is no neceſſity to prove it: the Court of <hi>France</hi> moreover makes her brags of it. We accuſe her, and ſhe glories in it. We agree the matter of Fact; the diſpute is onely concerning the Nature of it: Let the World judge whether it be juſt and honeſt for a Chriſtian Prince that would be thought ſo zealous a Catholick, to ſollicit the Forces of Infidels to overthrow and extirpate Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and whether the Emperor and the King of <hi>Spain</hi> have not more than ſufficient reaſon to abhor Peace with a Prince that declares War againſt <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> by uniting with the profeſs'd Enemies of the Croſs.</p>
            <p>The next Reaſon which the Marqueſs of <hi>Gaſtannage</hi> alledges is founded upon <hi>the unheard of Inhumanities, Cruelties and Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bariſms, perpetrated in the States of the Empire by the French Forces, by the peculiar Order of the moſt Chriſtian King.</hi> This was a ſound Argument, when our Governour produc'd it: but
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:93977:13"/>it is very much improv'd ſince that time, in regard thoſe Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are multiply'd ſince at a ſtrange rate. There was enough then to priviledge our Governor to ſpeak what he ſaid. But what might he not now have ſaid, had he ſeen what ſince has befall'n us? The fair Cities of <hi>Wormes, Spire,</hi> and <hi>Oppenheim,</hi> and all thoſe other Towns that lie upon the <hi>Rhine,</hi> from <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lipsburg</hi> to <hi>Mayence,</hi> have undergone the ſame Fate. That love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Canton</hi> of <hi>Germany,</hi> the Delight of the Earth, and true Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtrial Paradiſe, is now a dreadful Deſert; where there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to be ſeen but ſmoaking Ruins, the Crys of which mount up to Heaven. <hi>Spire,</hi> the Seat of Imperial Juſtice, where God voic'd forth his Oracles to determine the differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces between Man and Man, and preſerve the Peace of private Families, is at preſent a heap of Aſhes. The very Names of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Lineages are annihilated, the Seeds of Eternal Diſcord are ſown in the Ground, and the effects of the <hi>French</hi> Fury have extended themſelves even to future Ages, by the Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of ſo many <hi>German</hi> Families. <hi>Wormes,</hi> a ſpatious and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned City, is now become an Object that terrifies the Sight. Nothing but Ruins are there to be ſeen, which beſpeak the moſt execrable Cruelty that ever was committed. The whole Country round about preſents nothing to your view but Deſolation, not to be imagined. Neither Trees, nor Vineyards; no planted Orchards or Gardens: no Corn, no verdant Fields or Meadows, nor any hope of Harveſt. All is become one dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Object all alike: Conflagration, Fire and Aſhes: Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulation, intermix'd with ſmoaking heaps of Ruin and Rubbiſh. And what occaſion'd theſe Extravagant Outrages? Perhaps they might be done upon the firſt motions of an Indignation, not eaſily maſter'd. Perhaps it might be the effect of ſudden Rage, upon the Sacking of a City taken by Storm, where the Soldiers incens'd by the dangers they have eſcaped, and greedy of Plunder, put all to the Sword. No— it was in cold blood that theſe horrid Inhumanities were exercis'd; and upon Cities and Provinces, of which they had been in Poſſeſſion for ſeveral
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:93977:13"/>Months; upon People that endur'd their ſlavery with Patience, and of whom they had not the leaſt reaſon in the World to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain. It was done after mature Deliberations and Reſolutions taken in the Cabinet and Cabal at <hi>Verſailles,</hi> conſiſting of the King, <hi>Louvay,</hi> and <hi>de Croiſsy.</hi> Did ever the whole Senate of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils fix upon Reſolutions ſo horrid and Infernal? <hi>Lucifer</hi> and his Angels never imagin'd or executed any thing ſo diſmal, to the Deſtruction of Mankind. Suppoſe you ſaw the Inhabitants of that ſpacious and lovely Country hurrying out of the midſt of Fire and Flames; Mothers with their Infants in their Arms, bathing their Cheeks with Tears, and ſending up their piercing Crys to Heaven; diſconſolate Husbands dragging their Wives and Children after them; old Men ſlowly creeping from the danger, tottering at every ſtep, and bewailing the Loſs and Deſolation of a Country, where they had enjoy'd Tranquillity and Pleaſure for ſo many years together; young Men abandon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the hopes of thoſe Fortunes and Eſtates they were juſt ready to inherit by the Death of their Parents, whom old Age was about to diſpoſe to a better Life. Set before your Eyes this numerous Multitude diſpers'd among the Woods, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring over the Mountains, laden with thoſe ſmall remains of that ſame fatal Shipwreck which every one could ſave; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum'd with Wearineſs, over-whelm'd with Grief, ſurrounded with Affliction, and making the Banks of the River eccho with the Plaints and Lamentations.</p>
            <p>Laſtly conſider, that as an Accumulation of Cruelty, they refus'd theſe miſerable Creatures the Conſolation of ſeeking Sanctuary and Relief among their fellow Country-men beyond the <hi>Rhine.</hi> All that they deſir'd was to die Freemen, and to breath forth their laſt gaſp in the Arms of their Friends and Relations. But they conſtrain'd them only to change the Place of their Captivity, and to retire into the Cities, which the <hi>French</hi> as yet are Maſters of upon the <hi>Rhine;</hi> on purpoſe to redouble their Affliction, in ſeeing their abodes newly aſſign'd them, deſtin'd to the ſame Deſolation as their native Soil.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:93977:14"/>
            <p> In theſe firs of general Fury there was nothing ſpar'd. Things the moſt Sacred were prophan'd. The Biſhops and they that officiated at the Altars were dragg'd about the Streets in Pomp and Triumph. They were conſtrain'd to ſave thoſe ſorry Remnants which the Soldiers left, and what they could reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cue out of their Churches, among the Rocks and Foreſts. The Religious Orders were hal'd from their Solitudes, and the Spouſes of Chriſt were expos'd to the Inſolencies of the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious Soldiers. Thoſe Churches that were formerly the Sanctuaries of the unfortunate, were laid level with the Earth; the Devotion of our Anceſtors that rear'd them, not being able to preſerve them.</p>
            <p>Who would have thought or Age could have produced ſuch dreadful Extravagancies? And yet for all this, we are Debtors to the King of <hi>France.</hi> There needs no more to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh him from all the Princes in the World. Tho he was well enough known before by his new Law, while he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, that whatever had belonged, or had formerly been annex'd to the Countries which had been conceded to him by the Treaties of <hi>Munſter</hi> and <hi>Nimeghen,</hi> ought to return to him. Obſerve a Maxim of War, which is no leſs new, but very terrible: <hi>That there is a neceſſity of burning, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying, and annihilating whatever cannot be kept, leſt the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my ſhould make any benefit of it.</hi> Never was any concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Hell ſo dreadful. What would have become of the world if this Maxim had been in force two Ages ago? What would have become of <hi>Germany,</hi> during a War of fifty Years, from the unfortunate Overthrow of <hi>Frederick</hi> Elector <hi>Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,</hi> who aſpir'd to the Crown of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> to the Peace of <hi>Munſter.</hi> There is not a City in <hi>Germany</hi> that was not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected ſeveral times to the change of various Maſters. If a War were made upon their foundation, that nothing is to be left for the Enemy to make a benefit of, all the Cities in the World would be reduced to Aſhes.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:93977:14"/>
            <p> The <hi>Hollanders</hi> are happy in this, that that ſame Devil which now poſſeſſes <hi>France,</hi> did not enter her ſooner: For then the great City of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trecht,</hi> the Cities of <hi>Arnheim, Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meghen, Campen, Zwoll, Deventer, Doesburgh, Bommel, Thiel,</hi> and in a word, all the Towns of <hi>Guelders, Overyſſel,</hi> and the Province of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trecht</hi> which <hi>France</hi> abandon'd, had been ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly deſtroyed; the famous City of <hi>Meſſina</hi> had been like the top of Mount <hi>Gibello,</hi> not far diſtant from it.</p>
            <p>Has not our Governour reaſon enough to ſay, <hi>That the</hi> French <hi>have no regard to the Laws of Religion or War?</hi> We know that the Laws of War do authorize many Acts, which in Peace are look'd upon to be wicked and villainous. when we quit a City that we cannot keep, we carry away what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever may render it formidable to thoſe that are forc'd to leave it: We demand Ranſom, and take the chief Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants for Hoſtages. Nor were the <hi>French</hi> ignorant how to make the beſt Advantage of theſe Priviledges during the <hi>Dutch</hi> War. Thus alſo when we abandon any ſtrong Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſons, we take care to ruin the principal Fortifications. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, when we are ſorely preſt upon by the Enemy, Neceſſity conſtrains us to deſtroy whatever may be ſerviceable in the Country to the Enemies Army; VVe burn up the Hay, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry away the Corn, ſet on fire what we cannot carry away, and deſtroy all the Mills. But to fall without mercy upon Cities and Houſes, and to burn them and lay them in Aſhes, is a monſtruous and unparallel'd Extravagance, contrary to all the Laws of VVar: And then conſider the time, at the beginning of a VVar, before any Bruſh or Defeat received. So that it could be no fear of urging Miſchief that occaſion'd theſe Madneſſes. And now to what purpoſs is all this? Would the <hi>Germans</hi> and their Horſes have eaten the Walls of the magnificent Caſtle of <hi>Heydelbergh,</hi> or the Houſes of ſo many Cities, had they been left ſtanding? Are theſe the Proviſion and Amunition that maintain Armies? What tho the <hi>French</hi> had left the Cities of <hi>Heydelbergh, Manheim,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:93977:15"/>Frankendale, Spire, Worms,</hi> and <hi>Oppenheim,</hi> with their Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes entire, but empty however, without Corn, Wine, or Cattle, would the Enemy have been a whit the better; or at leaſt, would not they themſelves have been though to have ſome moderation in their Anger. But theſe Stones and theſe Houſes will remain eternal Witneſſes, that the Spirit of the <hi>French</hi> Cabal is a thouſand times worſe than that of the Turks, ſince the Infidels were never guilty of the like. 'Tis ſuch a reproach to the Chriſtian Name, that when the News of it ſhall reach the <hi>Ottaman</hi> Port, there is no doubt but all the Divan will lift up their hands to Heaven, and give God thanks for revenging them upon the Chriſtians by the Chriſtians themſelves, who commit thoſe heinous Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieties which their <hi>Janiſaries</hi> and <hi>Spahi</hi>'s would be afraid to do. And therefore, I wiſh that all <hi>Europe</hi> would make the following Reflections upon theſe enormous Irregularities of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt is, That <hi>France</hi> neither deſires, nor hopes for Peace, as Affairs ſtand: For ſhe leaves no room either to hope for, or to ask. Can we make a Peace with <hi>France</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reparation of our Damages? What ſatisfaction can ſhe give us for ſo many Wrongs? The Revenue of <hi>France</hi> for ten Years together, will never come near what we have reaſon to demand for above forty or fifty Cities burnt, and thirty Leagues of a fruitful and populous Country laid waſte and deſolate. Therefore <hi>France</hi> never deſires any Peace. 'Tis true, ſhe complains as if we intended to perpetuate the War by <hi>Alliances,</hi> wherein we engage our ſelves not to lay down Arms, till <hi>France</hi> be reduced to that condition wherein ſhe was after the Peace of <hi>Munſter.</hi> But indeed it is ſhe that would perpetuate the War, and render Peace impoſſible, by ſuch diſmal Deſolations. And then, ſince Peace is not the deſire of <hi>France,</hi> it behoves us never to give over till we have ſubdu'd her by War.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:93977:15"/>
            <p> The ſecond Reflection is, That ſince <hi>France</hi> is thus diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd, all the Allies muſt reſolve upon this, either to dye or vanquiſh, for there is no Medium. Therefore Generous <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> be aſſured, that whatever Cities you ſuffer her no take, will be only a Prey to her devouring Flames; and for that reaſon defend them to the laſt extremity. If you are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieg'd, bury your ſelves under your own Ruins, and periſh nobly.</p>
            <p>As for you <hi>Hollanders,</hi> whoſe Cities are the VVonders of the VVorld: Conſider likewiſe that if you are too ſparing of your ſelves, you will become a Prey to an Enemy that will not be ſparing of <hi>You,</hi> but lay your goodly Palaces all in Aſhes.</p>
            <p>And thou, the conquer'd Part of <hi>Flanders,</hi> and you <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bray, Valenciennes, S. Omer, Liſle, Tournay,</hi> and <hi>Douay,</hi> and the reſt that groan under the Bondage of <hi>France,</hi> behold in the Mirror of others Sufferings your own approaching Fate. For if the <hi>French</hi> are conſtrained to draw out their Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to reinforce their Armies, be aſſured they will ſet ye all on Fire, to the end you may be uſeleſs to their Enemies: Therefore take your opportunity betimes, to ſhake off ſo terrible a Yoke, and prevent ſo dreadful a Misfortune.</p>
            <p>And you the Cities of <hi>Brabant</hi> and <hi>Flanders,</hi> ſtill remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under the Dominion of your Lawful Sovereign, and make up one of the moſt lovely Ornaments of the Chriſtian VVorld be afraid of the ſame Fate, and be aſcertain'd that you will not eſcape it, if you fall into the hands of the <hi>French;</hi> and therefore be not Niggards either of your Money or Lives to anſwer the Expectations of that illuſtrious Governour, who is your <hi>Tutelar</hi> Angel.</p>
            <p>But as for you <hi>French. Men,</hi> accuſtom'd to Servitude for ſo many Years, in whoſe Breaſts there is nothing remaining of the old Generoſity of the Ancient <hi>Franks,</hi> do you believe your ſelves ſecure from theſe Outrages? Aſſure your ſelves you live under a Monarch who looks upon himſelf to be
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:93977:16"/>All in All, and all the VVorld to be nothing. At this time he burns and ranſacks <hi>Germany.</hi> He tells you, <hi>'Tis to ſave the State.</hi> But know, that he looks upon himſelf alone to be the State: And therefore, for his own preſervation he will burn you as he now burns his Neighbors. When the <hi>Germans</hi> ſhall be entered into <hi>Lorrain,</hi> be aſſur'd he will reduce <hi>Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paigne</hi> to the ſame condition with the Countries upon the <hi>Rhine;</hi> if they enter through <hi>Picardy,</hi> he will burn that alſo to ſecure himſelf; if we land an Army, he will burn <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandy</hi> to ſecure <hi>Verſailles.</hi> Neither are theſe Conjectures, for we have good Intelligence, and are well aſſur'd of it. Conſider therefore how to prevent the Crew of Firebrands, ſet your ſelves at Liberty, and lend your hands to thoſe that are ready to ſet you free.</p>
            <p>My laſt Reflection is, that as he makes War without giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any Quarter, ſo we ought to uſe as little Mercy in mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing War upon him. Not that we would counſel the Allies to deal by <hi>France,</hi> as the <hi>French</hi> have dealt by <hi>Germany</hi> (God forbid) We ought not to puniſh the Innocent for the Crimes of the guilty. We ought to ſpare the People, to deliver them from the Thraldom under which they groan, and to gain them by all manner of gentle Uſage. But as for thoſe that ſhall be found in Arms, thoſe Firebrands in pay under the moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive Burner in the World, by no means have any pity up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, but burn all thoſe Incendiaries without compaſſion. Let us not forbear chaſing them, till we come to the very Gates of that bloody cruel and fiery Cabal; that ſo thoſe deteſtable Counſellors may be forced to pay the full Penalty for all thoſe Calamities which their accurſed Counſels have brought upon all <hi>Europe.</hi> By this means we may be ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the moſt Chriſtian King himſelf; by delivering him out of the infamous Clutches of thoſe that tarniſh his Glory, and render him the common Enemy of all the Earth.</p>
            <trailer>The END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:93977:16"/>
            <head>Books Printed for <hi>ROBERT CLAVEL.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AN Account of the preſent State of <hi>Ireland,</hi> giving a full Relation of the new Eſtabliſhment made by the late K. <hi>James,</hi> as it was preſented to the Right Honorable the <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Shrewsbury,</hi> His Majeſties principal Secretary of State, and others of His Majeſties moſt Honorable <hi>Privy-Council.</hi> With an Account of what Sums of Mony, Arms, and number of Officers arrived there from <hi>France;</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the State of <hi>Derry</hi> and <hi>Eniskilling,</hi> and ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral other Affairs relating to that Kingdom, particularly of the Proceedings of the <hi>Parliament</hi> there.</p>
            <p>The Journal of the Proceedings of the <hi>Parliament</hi> in <hi>Ireland</hi> with the Eſtabliſhment of their Forces there.</p>
            <p>The Charge of ſubduing the <hi>Iriſh Rebellion,</hi> in 1641.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
